Laurie Beth Kalb Cosmo collection of New Mexico folklife documentation
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Exhibitions
  - Subseries 2: Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, 1976-1995
    - Notes and correspondence
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, Eulogio Ortega, 1988 (Box-folder 2/5)
        Eulogio Ortega request documentation from the Craft Museum about the loan of his santos.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, Gene Autry Museum (1/4), 1990; 1994, 2 color prints (4x6) (Box-folder 2/7)
        Includes object list, a layout of the exhibit and object labeling and descriptions.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary New Mexico Santos, notes from consultants meeting (2/4), January 27-28, 1992 (Box-folder 2/6)
        Handwritten notes taken at the January consultant meeting for Santos show with Charles Briggs, Barbara Kirshenblatt-Gimblett, Laurie Beth Kalb, Kevin Mulroy and Cynthia Hanisch.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, Gene Autry Museum (3/4), 1994, 1 color print (5x5) (Box-folder 2/8)
        Correspondence from Mark Lewis pertaining to the layout of the exhibit.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary New Mexico Santos, Autry Museum (4/4), 1994-1995, 2 black-and-white prints; 2 color slides (35 mm) (Box-folder 2/9)
        Contains correspondence with James H. Nottage, Joanne D. Hale, video treatment and press release. Also includes the slide that was used as the cover image for the exhibit.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, captions and prints for illustrations, undated, 19 color prints (3 1/2 x 5) (Box-folder 2/10)
        Captions for images displayed in the exhibit.
      - Crafting Devotions: Tradition in Contemporary, New Mexico Santos, LA Times Review, December 9, 1994 (Box-folder 2/11)
        Newspaper clippings about the exhibit.
    - Research slides, Submitted to editor Dana Asbury, University of New Mexico, for book publication (Autry museum and University of New Mexico Press).
      - Santo artists and artwork (1/2), AFC 2022/001:PH04-01 — PH04-135; 135 color slides (35 mm) (Box 10)
        Notes from original housing: 01: unlabeled item; 02: Wood for drums made at Red Shirt Indian Drum shop, Taso, New Mexico, 03-07: not labeled item; 08: Carving by Felix Lopez 3 figure abstract carving by Felix Lopez. Owned by the artist (1983); 09: unlabeled item; 10: Santos and Modern Sculpture by Feliz Lopez; 11: 1990 Spanish market display of Luis Barela, Jr.; 12-17: unlabeled item; 18: Abstract sculpture by Luis Tapia; 19: unlabeled item; 20: Taos Pueblo, Taos HH; 21: Frank Pinta, Santa Fe; 22: not labeled item; 23: Lion by Billy Rodriguez cont. section Spanish market (1989); 24-25: unlabeled; 26: Coyote, Chimayo, Robert Bal (1988); 27: Luis Tapia, Bird of Russian Olive, Santa Fe.(1984); 28: Modern sculpture by Feliz Lopez; 29: 8 interior of Tapas's studio; 30: Enrique Rendon, Velarde, New Mexico FF; 31-32: unlabeled; 33: Acrylic reproduction of W. Prathern photo by Edward Gonzales; 34: Stone Sculpture by Anglo modernist artist Kit Agri; 35: Enrique Rendon, Velarde, July 29, 1986; 36 -39: unlabeled; 40: Velarde, ER. 'P San Antonio's, 1976, 1986; 41: Velarde ER, hand carved donkey in brought? Cart; 42: St. Bernadette, Section IV, Velarde (1986); 43: Enrique Rendon (wood form Taos pueblo), Velarde, New Mexico; 44: Velarde, New Mexico, ER, San Francisca de arts; 45: Velarde ER, St. Jude? 46: Muerto IV by Enrique Rendon, Velarde; 47: Enrique Rendon, Velarde, New Mexico; 48: Enrique in backyard, Velarde, New Mexico; 49: Velarde, New Mexico, ER, San Martin de.; 50: By Enrique Rendon, carved by S and George Wheeler, Kateri Tekakwither; 51: Velarde E.R., Brown faced Guadalupe; 52: Velarde New Mexico, ER's brown faced Guadalupe; 53: Velarde New Mexico, San Martin; 54: Enrique Rendon retablo? San Francisco recent additions of, Velarde, New Mexico 00147; 55: [wooden statue of Jesus?]; 56: Felipe Archuleta, Tesuque, New Mexico; 57: Enrique Rendon's retablo, Velarde; 58: [2 wooden statues]; 59: Felipe Archuleta, Tesuque, New Mexico; 60: unlabeled; 61: Enrique Rendon, Velarde N.M. 1986, Guadalupe y Juan Diego, 1986; 62: Luis Tapia, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1883-1984, San Miguel, Our Lady of Sorrows, San Pedro Apostol; 63: China section of Moa, New Mexico interior of church, photo by LBK, 1984; 64: [Altar of religious statues]; 65: Velarde, New Mexico, 1sr visit (1984), E.R. Cristo; 66: Velarde, New Mexico, heads for Enrique's santos; 67: Velarde, 1976-1986, E.R. San Antonio's; 68: Velarde, 1976-1986, E.R. San Antonio's; 69: Velarde, muerte, ER; 70: Velarde, muerto, ER; 71: Velarde, muerto, ER; 72: Velarde, New Mexico, donkey made for bought cart; 73: Velarde, New Mexico, donkey made for bought cart; 74: Velarde, ER, 1976, San Antonio; 75: Taos, New Mexico, wood for drums made at Red skirt /Indian drum shop; 76: Velarde, ER, 1976, San Antonio; 77: Velarde, 1986, ER San Antonio; 78: Velarde, E.R. Santa Bernadette; 79: Velarde, E.R., Bows of Santos; 80: Velarde bows for Ers, santos; 81: Owned by Gere Kavanaugh, lamb by Felipe Archuletta; 82: Velarde ER, St. Jude; 83: Orlinda Lopez, Cordova, New Mexico; 84: Eurgencio Lopez, Cordova, New Mexico; 85: Charles Lopez, Cordova, New Mexico Eurgencios, San Miguel; 86: Charles Lopez, Cordova, New Mexico, 1983, San Miguel and the Dragon; 87: Enrique Rendon, Velarde, New Mexico; 88: Velarde, New Mexico, E.E. painting materials; 89: Elvid Levi Martinez, spanish market cont. section; 90: contemporary section, vspanish market, 19i89, Elvid Martinez; 91: Velarde, 1986, E.R. San Antonio; 92: Velarde, New Mexico, side view of Enrique's house including out? Buildings; 93: Verlade, New Mexico, Enrique Rendon; 94: Velarde, New Mexico E.R. Santa Teresa; 95: Velarde, New Mexico, prototype for E.R.'s images; 96: Velarde, New Mexico,v E.r. Santa Teresa; 97: Velarde, v1986, E.R. Santa Teresa; 98: Guadalupe and Juan Diego Potero Trading Post by Enrique Rendon; 99: Santa Teresa, Velarde, New Mexico, E.R.; 100: E.R., San Martin de Porres, Velarde, New Mexico; 101: E.R., Sam Martin de Porres, Velarde, New Mexico; 102: Enrique Rendon, Velarde, New Mexico, summer 1983; 103: Velarde, New Mexico, Backside of St. Francis table; 104: Taos Pueblo; 105: Velarde, New Mexico, E.R. Santa Teresa; 106: unlabeled item; 107: Velarde, New Mexico, Prototype for E.R. image; 108: Prototype for E.R. image; 109: Velarde, New Mexico, Enrique Rendon backyard; 110: Velarde, New Mexico, E.R's painting materials; 111: Enrique Rendon, San Cajetan; 112-118: unlabeled item; 119: Trastero by Luis Tapia pine, tempera; 120: Abstract woodcarvings by Patrocinio Barela ca 1930s WPA, Feliz Lopez ca. 1982, Celso Gallegos, ca 1930s; 121 -135: unlabeled.
      - Santo artists and artwork (2/2), AFC 2022/001:PH04-136 — PH04-255; 109 color slides (35 mm) (Box 11)
        Notes from original housing: 136: Eulogio Ortega, Spanish market '84, San Isidro; 137: unlabeled; 138: Ramon Lopez, Spanish market, 1990; 139 - 140: unlabeled; 141: Feria Artesana, Albuquerque, 1983, Gloria Lopez Cordova in her both; 142: Luis Lujan, 1988, San Pedro Apostol; 143: Santa Lucia, 1988, Nambe by Luisito Lujan; 144: unlabeled; 145: unlabeled; 146: Sculpture by Egri, Taos, New Mexico; 147: Luis Tapia, ca. 1990, Holy Family; 148: Santa Lucia, 1988, Nambe by Luisito Lujan; 149 -255: unlabeled.
    - Undated photographs
      Notes from original housing: Illustrations for Crafting Devotions in Contemporary New Mexico Santos, Autry Museum, 1994.
      - Images for book (1/3), AFC 2022/001: PH04-256 — PH04-346; 88 color transparency film (4x5) (Box 3)
        Notes from original housing: 256: intro p. 3.; 257: intro p. 6; 258: intro p.7; 259: intro p. 10; 260: intro p. 15; 261: intro p. 15; 262: 2.18, 263: Tapia p. 29; 264: Tapia p. 7; 265: Tapia p. 7; 266: Tapia p. 15; 267: Tapia p. 16; 268: Barela p. 1; 269: Barela p. 4; 270: Barela p. 7; 271: Barela p. 16; 272: Barela p. 25; 273: Barela p. 26; 274: Barela p. 26; 275: Barela p. 30; 276: Marco p. 24; 277: Marco p.26; 278: Marco p.27; 279: Marco p. 30; 280: Marco p. 30; 281: Marco p.41; 282: Rendon p.2; 283: Rendon p.2; 284: Rendon p.8; 285: Rendon p.18; 286: Rendon p.30; 287: Rendon p.35; 288: Rendon p.38; 289: Rendon p.39; 290: Rendon p.40; 291: Rendon p.40; 292: Conclusion 293-301: unlabeled; 303 -337: unlabeled; 339 -344: unlabeled.
      - Images for book (2/3), AFC 2022/001: PH04-302; 1 black-and-white transparency film (4x5) (Box 3)
      - Images for book (3/3), AFC 2022/001: PH04-338; 1 color transparency film (2 1/2 x 2 1/2) (Box 3)
      - Artist, undated, AFC 2022/001: PH04-345 — PH04-346; 2 color slides (35 mm) (Box 11)
        Victor Goler
- Series 3: Academic Works
  - Papers and theses
    - From market to home: The Domestic environment of a Contemporary Santero, Masters Thesis, 1985, 7 black-and-white and 2 color prints (Box-folder 2/12)
    - From market to home: The Domestic environment of a Contemporary Santero, AFS paper printouts, 1985 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Cultural Conservation Project: From the Coffee shop to the canyon: women's personal experiences and the architectural history, Northeast New Folklife Survey, AFS paper, 1986 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Santos, Statutes and Sculpture Contemporary Woodcarving from New Mexico: AFS Conference, October 26-30, 1988 (Box-folder 2/15)
      Conference held in Cambridge, MA.
    - JAF Review of Hispanic-American material culture, Laurie Beth Kalb, 1989 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Kalb Review of Community and Continuity: The history, architecture and cultural landscape of La Tierra Amarilla, New Mexico, 1991 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Crafting Tradition: Spanish colonial santo production by Marco and Patricia Oviedo, AFS Paper, 1992 (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Lecture to Anthropology Faculty Harvard University: Crafting Tradition: Modernism, Primitivism and the Cultural Ownership of Woodcarvings by Taos Artist Patrocinio Barela, 1994 (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Imaging the West Symposium 1995: Interpretive Strategies Among New Mexico Santeros: The "Other" as Image Maker, June 11, 1995, 29 color slides (35mm) and manuscript materials (Box-folder 2/20)
      Symposium at the Autry Museum of Western Heritage, Los Angeles. Includes paper that was presented, 29 color slides (35 mm), registration form and a brochure.
    - Various artists and Spanish market, 1990, AFC 2022/001: PH06-01 — PH06-28; 28 color slides (35 mm) (Box 11)
      Notes from original housing: 01:Santa Fe, Spanish market, 1884. Photo by D. Flynn 1, Thomas Sena?; 02: Leo Salazar and display on his woodcarvings at 1990 Spanish market; 03-04: unlabeled; 05: 5 "abstract;" 06-07: unlabeled; 08: Oviedo; 09 -28: unlabeled
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, Thomas Merlan, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 2/21)
      Cosmo seeking permission to use The Merlan's family collection of Patrocinio Barela's materials for her dissertation.
    - Correspondence, Richard Ahlborn, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/22)
      Correspondence between Richard Ahlborn and Cosmo pertaining to her Smithsonian Fellowship. Also included is Cosmo's report of the fellowship.
    - Correspondence for dissertation, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2/23)
      Review of dissertation by Roger Abrahams, Charles Briggs and Burt Feintuch.
  - Taos
    - TAOS, 1986 (Box-folder 2/24)
      Article pertaining to Cosmo and her new position at the museum including congratulatory letters.